Ben Butterworth ben@orth.uk

London, UK [Website, Stack Overflow]

I'm often torn between making things to help people and tinkering with tech. I design and build for change. I've worked on distributed systems, machine learning, 3D web, and mobile apps. On the side, I make apps, write on Stack Overflow (top 2%), give talks, write articles (10K visitors/month), & open source (e.g. push). I received dean's list & distinction for computer science & engineering degrees. I don't leetcode, I ChatGPT.

### WORK EXPERIENCE

Senior Software Engineer at Helsing (Rust, Python, Typescript, Postgres)

Jan 2022-now

- Design & implement Node API Gateway for frontend application with tRPC, zod & typescript.
- Design, deploy & maintain system with Docker/Kubernetes/Helm onto Azure & edge clusters.
- Develop infrastructure/features so anyone can use product internally (including preview env)
- Built SDKs for Al applications, to handle configuration, observability & lifecycle, including improving performance of real-time Al applications in resource-constrained environments.
- Improved system design with design docs, SDK/API design, and domain-driven design.
- Built automation tools, e.g. protobuf package generation for Rust, Python and Typescript.
- Develop free & open-source GPS and orientation data collection app used by field teams
- Developed, documented & tested drone application, including automated simulations tests.
- Writing fast unit/integration tests with high test coverage (e.g. 92%) and giving workshops.

### Flutter SDK Developer at Ably.com (Flutter, Swift, Kotlin)

Apr 2021-Dec 2021

- Nominated for the award, "bias for action" on my last week of work at Ably
- Oversee development by contractors working on WebSocket SDKs (iOS and Android)
- Added push notification and encryption support to WebSocket <u>package</u>, abstracting iOS / Android APIs into Flutter API, e.g. spawning Flutter Engine for background processing.
- Found bugs in internal and open-source code, providing actionable bug reports & fixes
- Built an anonymous video calling app (<a href="https://club2d.orth.uk">https://club2d.orth.uk</a>) which generates a 3D face mesh, rendering it other user's browsers in real time. Gave talk at JSMonthly.
- Maintaining open-source libraries: creating changelogs, writing documentation, handling issues and supporting enterprise customers
- Fixing and enhancing documentation on the Ably documentation site covering all SDKs
- Contributed Flutter Engine PR to enhance Flutter plugin development on iOS.

Machine Learning Engineer at Popsa (TensorFlow, Python, Kotlin, Swift) Sep 2020 - Apr 2021

- Designed and built on-device photo library face recognition feature, including parallel image processing and IO, profiling and optimising memory and throughput across devices
- Built photo albums title suggestions using EXIF data, using Protocol-buffer based APIs.

- Wrote NumPy files parser in Kotlin to investigate cross platform image processing inconsistencies and subsequently discovering a bug in Android graphics library.
- Optimized models with additional layers and pre-processing to improve performance
- Built internal tools for data scientists, including Python applications and macOS CLI tool to run models, including distribution for macOS (notarization) and progress animations.

# Software Engineer (Mobile Team) at Ocado Technology

Feb 2019 - Sep 2019

- Designed mobile-friendly APIs for mobile application offering sold to other supermarkets
- Reduced response time for requests by 3x, 1.24s to 0.39s by merging related APIs.

# **Product Engineer** at Emberton

Sep 2017 - Jan 2019

- Migrated vulnerable/exploited systems into secure and usable products (Gmail, GDrive)
- Designed (sketching, 3D modeling) products for hotel rooms, e.g. iron & iron board holder

# **EDUCATION**

Imperial College, Master's in Computer Science, Distinction (highest)

1 year

- C++, OOP, Computer vision, ML, Information Security, Networking and Distributed Systems.
- Thesis: comparing/ implementing real-time ML systems for the edge and in cloud.
- Built receipt scanning app and invited to present and meet start-up with £150m investment.
- Published mobile app to help 'calculate carbon impact of food' on Apple Store / Play Store, using React Native, GraphQL and Google cloud functions.
- Built landing page in React and GatsbyJS in 4 hours: <a href="https://foodprint.orth.uk">https://foodprint.orth.uk</a>.

## Imperial College, Master's in Engineering, 1st class (highest), Dean's list

4 years

- Developed painting machine using Arduino, Solidworks, 3d printing and CNC machining
- Business School courses: Project Management (A\*) and Strategic Management (A\*).

#### Massachusetts Institute of Technology, exchange student

6 months

- Courses: Intro to Algorithms, Entrepreneurship in Engineering, Intro to Machine Learning.
- Research assistant: Analysed molecular simulation data for <u>publications</u> using Python.

## **VOLUNTEERING, HOBBIES & AWARDS**

- Built <u>demo app</u> & gave workshop for annotating images with bounding boxes for ML training, using Flutter, and Cloudflare (D1/SQLite on the edge, Workers, R2 object storage, etc).
- Developed open-source push notifications Flutter package and presented at GDGDevFest
- Developed & published <u>GPS/orientation Flutter app</u> (<u>iOS</u>, <u>Android</u>).
- Self-taught ML engineering and TensorFlow, achieving the <u>TensorFlow Developer Certificate</u>.
- Organising and running events for 800 students in Halls, given Imperial Volunteer award.
- Managing websites, releases and DNS for customers, organisations and personal projects.
- Author of technical articles & guides on <a href="https://orth.uk">https://orth.uk</a>, averaging 10K unique visitors a month, with one article gaining 33K unique visitors in 3 days and top of <a href="https://orth.uk">Hacker News</a>.